Guide to the Waldo Greene collection of Thornton Wilder papers, 1928-1994 MS 484
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Waldo Greene collection of Thornton Wilder papers
1928-1994
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Wilder, Thornton
MS 484
4 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
This collection is comprised of materials which Waldo Greene, a student of Thornton Wilder's, gathered about Wilder during Wilder's lifetime and up until Greene's death. Included among these materials are correspondence, bibliographies, newspaper and journal clippings, photographs, playbills, and copies of Wilder's typewritten journals.
Biographical Note
Waldo Greene was born ca. 1906 and died in 1994. At age seventeen he was a student of Thornton Wilder, then a French teacher at an exclusive prep school in New Jersey. Greene, a seventeen year old student at the time Wilder taught him, came to Texas after World War II, married and remained in the Rio Grande Valley.
Greene spent much of his life seeking details about his former teacher's life and collecting memorabilia about him. He corresponded with Wilder and Wilder's sister after Wilder's death.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of comprises the materials Waldo Greene, a student of Thornton Wilder's, gathered about Wilder during Wilder's lifetime and up until Greene's death. Included among these materials are correspondence, bibliographies, newspaper and journal clippings, photographs, playbills, and copies of Wilder's typewritten journals.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Waldo Greene donated the bulk of the materials, including a book collection in 1981. He continued to add to the collection until 1993.
Arrangement
Missing Title
Series I: Biographical
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Writings
Series IV: Clippings
Series V: Memorabilia
Index Terms
Subjects
Dramatists, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Biography; Literature
Document Types
corrrespondence; journals (accounts); clippings (information artifacts); photographs
Subjects (Persons)
Wilder, Isabel; Greene, Waldo; Wilder, Thornton
- Series I: Biographical, 27270
  - Thornton Wilder Biographical Materials, 27273 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronology of Thornton Wilder, 27272 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bibliography, 27271 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Correspondence, 27242
  Scope and Contents note
  The Correspondence includes handwritten and photocopied letters to various people from Wilder. Also included in this series is correspondence from Waldo Greene to various people regarding Wilder, his whereabouts at certain times, or asking for explanations about correspondents. There are letters between Greene and manuscript dealers regarding Wilder materials for sale. Finally there are letters from Isabel Wilder about her brother, about Greene's collecting of Wilder memorabilia, and personal notes about the friendship that was formed between the Wilders and the Greenes.
  - Wilder Letters to the Bentleys, 1946-1952, n.d.; 27269 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wilder Letters to Roger Brooks, 1968, 1975; 27268 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wilder Letters to Ludi Clare, 27267 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wilder Letters to Peggy Clifford, 1958-1975, n.d.; 27266 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Wilder Letters to Julian Cornell, 1950-1951; 27265 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wilder Letters to Katherine Cornell, 1941, 1965, 1970; 27264 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wilder Poem to John Craven, 1938; 27263 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Wilder Letters to Waldo Greene, 1929, 1931, 1932, 1935, 1937-1942, 1944, 1945; 27262 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wilder Letters to Waldo Greene, 1952-1975; 27261 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Envelopes of Letters from Wilder to Greene, 27260 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Wilder Letters to Walter Hickens, 27259 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Wilder Letters to the Isaacs, 1927-1941; 27258 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Wilder Letters to Winifred Scott, 1949; 27257 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Wilder Letters to Katherine M. Wygant, 27256 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Wilder Letters to various people, 1928-1949; 27255 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Wilder Letters to various people, 1950-1975, n.d.; 27254 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photocopies Wilder Letters to Various People, 1929-1981; 27253 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence between Greene and various people regarding Wilder, 1960-1979; 27252 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters to Greene regarding Wilder Memorabilia, 27251 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters to Greene regarding Wilder Memorabilia, 1978-1982; 27250 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Greene regarding Wilder Memorabilia, 1983-1986; 27249 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Greene regarding Wilder Memorabilia, 1989-; 27248 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Isabel Wilder to Waldo Greene, 27247 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Letters from Isabel Wilder and Amos Wilder to Waldo Greene, 27246 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Greene's notes from visits with Irene Wilder, 27245 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notecards, 27244 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, 27243 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series III: Writings, 27219
  The Writings series consists of playbills of many of Wilder's plays, copies of several of the plays including one in Arabic, several articles written by Wilder and typescript copies of Wilder's journal.
  - Subseries A: Playbills, 27232
    - 42nd Street, 27241 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - The Alcestiad, 27240 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Hello Dolly, 27239 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Long Christmas Dinner, 27238 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - The Matchmaker, 27237 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Plays for Bleeker Street, 27236 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Our Town, 27235 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - The Skin of Our Teeth, 27234 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - The Unicorn of Big-City Hotels, 27233 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Subseries B: Plays, 27227
    - Love and How To Cure It, 27231 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Matchmaker, 27230 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Our Town, 27229 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - The Trumpet Shall Sound, 27228 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Subseries C: Articles, 27225
    - "The Silent Generation," from Current Thinking and Writing, 27226 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subseries D: Journals, 27220
    - Journal of T.N. Wilder - 1st Typing of Manuscript, D.G. Gallup, editor, 27224 (Box 4, Folder 4-7)
    - Thornton Wilder Journals, pages 1-176, 1939-1961; 27223 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Thornton Wilder Journals, pages 177-362, 1939-1961; 27222 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - This Journal, 27221 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
- Series IV: Clippings, 27212
  The Clippings series consists of clippings that Greene collected during Wilder's life and after his death. Topics range from publication of new work, to openings of plays, to events in Wilder's life.
  - Notes and Clippings pertaining to Thornton Wilder, 27218 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1927- 1960's; 27217 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1989; 27216 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1987-1990; 27215 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Copy of Transcript of CBS Coverage of Wedding of United Kingdom's Prince Charles to Lady Diana Spencer, mention of Thornton Wilder, 1981; 27214 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Magazines with articles about Thornton Wilder, 27213 (Box 7-10)
- Series V: Memorabilia, 27209
  - Lighter, 27211 (Box 11)
  - Drawing and Fabric Swath of Costume for Dolly Levi - Hello Dolly (Hello Dolly was a remake of Wilder's play The Matchmaker.), 27210 (Box 11)